<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of Carolina with advice to the setlers by R.F.</title>
            <author>R. F.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F52A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12010944</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12010944</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1009:27 or 1652:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of Carolina with advice to the setlers by R.F.</title>
                  <author>R. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bringhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Duplicate copies appear on reels 1009 and 1652.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>South Carolina --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>North Carolina --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52413:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Preſent State OF CAROLINA WITH <hi>Advice to the Setlers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By R. F.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> at the Sign of the Book in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52413:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52413:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Preſent State OF CAROLINA, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>AROLINA is part of the Main in <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and ſo much celebrated by Mounſier <hi>Laudonere,</hi> that he entitles it <hi>Florida,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of her florid, and fragrant fields, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſh't with flowers, that perfume the air: whoſe ſweet ſcituations, by reaſon of moſt delicious and pleaſant meadows (and flouriſhing ſavana's) adorns the Continent; and whoſe benevolent breſt ſends daily ſupplies to the planter, and hourly relief to the poor and neceſſitous native: whoſe ſpacious arms (<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s if circulating the Ocean) proclaims her ſhores ſanctuary to diſtreſſed Marriners; and a generous protection to deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seamen, that ſolicit refreſhment from her repleniſh't Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, which extend themſelves ſouthward to the River <hi>St.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52413:3"/>Matheo,</hi> in twenty nine degrees, odd minutes; ſo dilates to <hi>Luck Iſland,</hi> near <hi>Roanoak</hi> on the promontories of <hi>Virginia,</hi> in thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſix degrees north latitude (now called <hi>Albemarle</hi>) a large and ſpacious ſettlement, conſiſting of ſome two or three thouſand inhabitants; upon a fertil Soil, and a rapid River, whoſe Bar by reaſon its ſo ſtreight and ſhallow, a Veſſel of conſiderable port and burden is deny'd admittance into the bowel of the Collony.</p>
            <p>But the late and flouriſhing ſettlement lies yet more ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly, in and about thirty two degrees, odd minutes; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel with <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine:</hi> and equals the height of <hi>Bermudos,</hi> upon the na<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igable Rivers of <hi>Cooper,</hi> and <hi>Aſhly,</hi> formerly known by the names of <hi>Wando,</hi> and <hi>Kiawah<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And there is a Bar alſo, tho undeſervedly calumniated by prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate perſons, who would if poſſible unhinge the ſettlement when becauſe to emulate and envy their Neighbours proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity. But to clear that Objection, this Bar has ſeveral Channels, and the deepeſt at low water is eighteen foot; and the ſhalloweſt about eleaven, and twelve foot; which is depth enough for any navigating Veſſel of three or four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred tun; ſince at high water the tide ſwells to ſix and eight foot perpendicular.</p>
            <p>This is that famous CAROLINA, which his Majeſty the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> has united to his Emperial Crown; &amp; by his Royal Grant eſtabliſhed it a Province; and has dignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it a Principality: which by conſent amongſt the Lords i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> transferr'd to the eldeſt Proprie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or. But the Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etors are eight in number, and their Names and Titles as followeth. <hi>Lord Chancellor Clarendon, Lord Duke Albemarle,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52413:3"/>Earl of Craven, Lord Anthony Aſhley Cooper Earl</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury, Lord John Berkly, Sr George Carteret, Sr William Berkly,</hi> and <hi>Sr John Colleton Knight and Baronet.</hi> Theſe are the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors, whoſe Laws and Government (becauſe to proceed in my deſcription) is ſuſpended till farther Opportunity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to uſher them in.</p>
            <p>So that now to deſcribe the preſent ſtrength of the ſouthern ſettlement of the <hi>flouriſhing Carolina</hi> (by modeſt computation) we calculate their Artillery to fourteen, or fifteen hundred re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, and gallant fighting men; under excellent conduct, and diſcipline; as well arm'd as moſt men, &amp; as well as any Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny provided with Amunition. Their Women alſo are health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and fruitful; and their Children generally beautiful, and ſtrong. Nor have we hitherto conſidered the Negro Slaves, whoſe labour proclaims the Setlers plenty; and whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice doubles their ſecurity, if provided a Foreigner ſhould attempt to invade them. Moreover it enervates the femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine Native, if at any time he conſpires againſt the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, who can never be inſenſible of the natural antipathy the <hi>Native,</hi> and the <hi>Negro</hi> has one againſt another; which the rather confirms the Setlers ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Heavens ſhine upon this famous Country the ſoveraign Ray of health; and has bleſt it with a ſerene Air, and a lofty Skie, that defends it from noxious Infection; nor is there any known Diſtemper incident to the inhabitant whereby to terrify, and affright him; who for the moſt part lives by the law of plenty, extended to the utmoſt limits of ſanity: This bleſſing one would think was encouragement enough; when if barely to contemplate the conſideration
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52413:4"/>of health. But Heaven, that alwaies attends our mortal feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, directs to ſtars more propicious; pointing out to us the beaten path of the Patriarchs, and led on by a glorious view of the Apoſtles, makes ſhine the blazing torch of the Goſpel; whereby to promote the unity and harmony of piety in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that Vertue may grow up into divine practice, and the purity of every pious profeſſion bloſſom, and flouriſh to the utmoſt ends of the ſettlement in <hi>Carolina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for as much as the motives of health and riches are inducements ſtrong enough to ſummons people from the ends of the earth; who ſo ridiculous to repute them vain and unprofitable Arguments to encourage the people of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſince from divers Inland Towns (and various Ports of <hi>England</hi>) ſeveral Natives, and Forreigners have directed their courſe by proſperous Stars to the florid, and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fields in <hi>Carolina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in <hi>America</hi> (to my own obſervation) ſeveral Families have tranſported themſelves from the ports of <hi>Barbados;</hi> but what from the reſt of the <hi>Caribes,</hi> I know not: yet am credibly inform'd (and from very good hands) that divers are gone, and going from thence: as alſo from <hi>New-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, Bermudos, New-York, New-Jerſey, New-England, Long-Iſland, De-la-ware, Maryland,</hi> and <hi>Virginia;</hi> but great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſeveral from the borders of <hi>Ireland:</hi> beſides divers good Ships, with ſome eminent Families that are lately gone off from the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> of whom we have an accompt of their ſafe arrival in <hi>Carolina,</hi> bleſt with a proſperous Paſſage. But the hopeful progreſs of this flouriſhing Country invights ſome Northern <hi>Americans</hi> to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52413:4"/>emulate ſuch ſacred ſanctuary as without ſacrilidge is tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to people of tender Conſcience. Moreover, its a ſalubrous Air to the ſick, and diſeaſed; and a generous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivement to neceſſitous, and abject Families; as alſo the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſuch as ſtudy to be rich. Engins ſtrong enough one would think to induce mankind to hope the proſperity of this famous Settlement.</p>
            <p>But the ſettlement of <hi>Albemarle</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Roan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oak</hi>) preſents firſt to our view; and is the oldeſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt northern County in the fair Province of <hi>Carolina;</hi> ſcituated about thirty five degrees, and odd minutes north la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: from whoſe repleniſhed Meadows (as alſo from the more ſouthern inhabitants) as good Beef, and Pork is ſaved, and ſent off to <hi>Barbados,</hi> and other the <hi>Caribe</hi> Iſlands; as art and induſtry can husband.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Aſhley</hi> County is yet more ſouthward, and lies ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated thirty two degrees, forty five minutes; where the Setlers and Inhabitants toil not in ſummer to accommodate themſelves with winter's proviſion: becauſe hitherto they have conſidered it uſeleſs, and altogether unneceſſary for the Planter to employ his hands, and ſtrength, where Nature ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally ſtocks them with Herbage: &amp; the winter, becauſe ſo ſoftened with a moderate Air, repreſents it much of the caſt and temperament with our <hi>March</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and that's as much as to conſider it the relique only of a milde, and ſhort winter; or rather the ſurprizal of an approaching ſpring, that breathes forth to iniciate the ſummer: which if barely to contemplate, reanimates the vital ſences; and ſolidly to poſſeſs, refreſhes both Native and Inhabitant. And here it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52413:5"/>is that their Ships are built, and dreſt up by <hi>Bermudian</hi> hands, the moſt approved Marriners; and a general error if not the beſt navigating Ships in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now by way of Advice; the firſt thing requiſit and neceſſary for the ſetler to embrace, is to fall Timber, and to clear the Ground (which is reaſonably undertaken, as by an <hi>Advertiſement</hi> in the laſt Paragraph) as ſome already have done, and planted Potatos, the Caſſaida Root, Yams, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Carrots, Cabbidges, Onyons, Turnips, Parſnips, Shelots, (but they grow naturally there) Colleflowers, Artichokes, Musk-Melons, and Water-Melons; beſides Wormwood, Nep, Scurvy-graſs, Rue, Meadſweet, Trefoil, Cinquefoil, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane (Annis, Cububs, and Cardamome Seeds) Radiſhes, and Horſe-Radiſhes; Mellelot, Angellica, Arch-Angel, Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, Thime, Lettice, Spinage, Sweetmarjarum, Sommer &amp; Winterſavory, Endive, Succory, Hopps, Water Creſſes, Cena, &amp; China Root, with other Druggs, &amp; Saxafrage, Saſſafras, and Saſſaperrilla: beſides divers other Vegetables without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: &amp; Licoris beyond diſpute muſt of neceſſity thrive admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably well there; for in many places its a moiſt bottom, and an open ground, becauſe lying ſo near the Springs, and in a gravelly ſoil, little or nothing differing from <hi>Worſhop</hi> in <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghamſhire;</hi> where they dig up the beſt Licoris in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, all ſorts of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Grane, as Wheat, Rye, Barley, Peas, Beans, Oates, Lentills, Fitches, and <hi>Indian</hi> Corn, with other <hi>European</hi> and <hi>American</hi> Roots, and Plants; which <hi>Carolina</hi> beyond diſpute with ſmall induſtry will produce as large, and as good as the World has. For you are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what by Art, and the Law of Neceſſity we compel to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52413:5"/>grow in a cold climate; nature of her ſelf protrudes, and thruſts forth there; becauſe of the ſovereign warmth from this generous latitude. Nor is the heat at any time ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant whereby to ſuffocate the air with intemperance, becauſe deſtinated under the temperate Zone, which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes neither of the Extreams of the one, or the other; and which alſo invights every thing to vegetate with admirable ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>The next thing worthy our conſideration, is their plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eating; becauſe having their accomodation very cheap within themſelves; where Beef two years ſince was ſold at twelve ſhillings a hundred, and Pork at the rate of ſixteen: ſo that Cattel (you may read) begins to be plentiful, and Hoggs of a prodigious encreaſe. There is a Gentleman, one Mr. <hi>Andrew Percival,</hi> the now preſent Agent to the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> (I know the <hi>Gentleman</hi> very well) who by his own induſtry (Providence guiding) has raiſed and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from One Hundred Head of Cattel, to more than One Thouſand, in leſs than ſeven years; and moſt of thoſe Cattel very fair, and large-headed Beaſts, now grazing up and down in beautiful Savana's; little or nothing inferiour to our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Meadows. Yet beſides Mr. <hi>Percival,</hi> there are ſeveral other induſtrous Setlers, and Planters, that proſper very well; though not having by much ſo large, and ſo conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a ſtock to begin with.</p>
            <p>Moreover, there are Barrows (which by reaſon of the ſuperabundant plenty of Maſt, and Roots in thoſe parts) that ſome have weighed three, and four hundred weight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece; and ſuch had the <hi>Lady Yeomans,</hi> as I am credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52413:6"/>who had Four Hundred Hoggs in a Herd, and Five Hundred Turkies in a drove; beſides Dunghil Fouls too numerous to relate without ſuſpition. And which Plantation of hers, conſiſting of one thouſand five hundred Acres, was by the induſtry of one Mr. <hi>James Moore</hi> (an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) cleared from Charge in ſome three years time; and with the natural produce of the Country only: which am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifies the great fertility of the ſoil, that together with the encreaſe of Beef, and Pork, which if well ſaved, and ſent off to other Parts (as ſome has already been ſent to <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos</hi>) muſt of neceſſity bring in conſiderable Profit.</p>
            <p>So that now ſince the arrival of Captain <hi>Dunbar</hi> (diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch't from <hi>England</hi> with Paſſengers in the <hi>Richmond Frigot</hi>) the Vineroons and Inhabitants there buſie themſelves very much about planting of Vineyards, to make Wine; and dreſſing of Oliveyards, to get Oyl. But ſome go upon Cotten, and other ſome propound to go upon Silk, becauſe having the Mulberry Tree in every angle of the Province: and upon Tobacco, ſome already have made their attempts, with admirable ſucceſs; for upon due examination, its little or nothing inferiour to <hi>Virina.</hi> Hempſeed, and Flax alſo has been ſowed, and yields admirable produce; which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encourages the Manufacture for Linnen, as alſo for Sail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and Cordidge.</p>
            <p>Upon Honey ſome have ſtrong inclinations, when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe having ſuch variety of Flowers (and Bloſſoms) that invights to accommodate the Laborous Bee; where, as by experience, they become ſo prolifick, as frequently to ſwarm four times in a year; and ſuch was the encreaſe from one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52413:6"/>ſingle Hive, brought over from <hi>Bermudos (tho Half of them were loſt at Sea)</hi> that within leſs than two full years, Captain <hi>Morris Matthews</hi> (<hi>an induſtrous Gentleman, who mannages Lievtenant Collonel</hi> James Colleton<hi>'s Plantation</hi>) had a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce of more than Ten Hives; beſides a <hi>Preſentation</hi> made to the <hi>Governour</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>Now ſome are thinking to intangle themſelves with the conſideration of Rape, and Linſeed for Oyl: but the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian-Natives</hi> get a ſweet Oyl out of the <hi>Hickery Nutt,</hi> which is much of the nature of our <hi>Engliſh Walnutt;</hi> but not ſo racy, nor the Kernel ſo plump, and pleaſant; and this Oyl they ſell for Beads and Trifles of little or no value: which Oyl may be much more improved, and ſubſtituted in lieu of <hi>Oyl Olives.</hi> So that ſtaple Commodities of <hi>Carolina</hi> will be <hi>Wine, Oyl, Silk, Hides, Wool, Tallow, Honey, Bees-wax, Tobacco, Hemp, Flax, Linning</hi> and <hi>Wolling Cloth; Pitch, Tar, Cordidge,</hi> and <hi>Maſts for Shipping:</hi> beſides an additional Manufacture is that of the <hi>Camlet Gote,</hi> intended thither by the Right Honourable the <hi>Earl of</hi> SHAFTSBVRY, as a new Encouragement to animate the people to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry.</p>
            <p>Here are very tall, large, and ſtrait Timber-Trees <hi>(the World has not better)</hi> and ſuch is the <hi>Aſh;</hi> the <hi>White,</hi> the <hi>Red,</hi> and the <hi>Live Oak:</hi> but the <hi>Cyprus Tree</hi> grows to an amazing bigneſs; as alſo the <hi>Walnutt,</hi> and <hi>Hickery</hi> or <hi>American Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutt,</hi> already expreſt. Here alſo are ſtately and tall <hi>Cedars,</hi> both White, and Red, that cover the Earth. And the <hi>Pine,</hi> with the <hi>Aſp,</hi> and <hi>Poplar,</hi> that grow to an incredible mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude: beſides ſeveral other <hi>Timber Trees,</hi> that I cannot at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52413:7"/>preſent remember. There is alſo the <hi>Birch,</hi> the <hi>Beech,</hi> the <hi>Willow,</hi> the <hi>Sallow,</hi> the <hi>Alder,</hi> the <hi>Elm,</hi> the <hi>Sicamore,</hi> the <hi>Mulberry,</hi> and the <hi>Figg Tree;</hi> but they grow every where: and the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatoon,</hi> &amp; <hi>Peach</hi> is common, without Cultivation; yet no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Stone Fruit is obſerved in <hi>Europe,</hi> than what naturally grows wild in <hi>America. Vines</hi> alſo ſpread themſelves to ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour the Trees in every Wood: and <hi>Strawberries</hi> ſtrew themſelves in every Field. But <hi>Violets,</hi> I had almoſt forgot them, becauſe the Inhabitants depreſs them, by treading them under foot; yet they, with various other Flowers, perfume the Air. And <hi>Roſes,</hi> they ſprout up ſo plentifully in every Plantation, that the Planters themſelves are think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therewith to make Fences. And where all other Roots and Fruit Trees thrive to a Miracle; as the <hi>Orange Tree, Lemon Trees,</hi> and <hi>China Orange Trees, Quince Trees, Cherry Trees, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Trees, Pear Trees, and Prickle Pears,</hi> that bear twice a year. Then there's the <hi>Almond,</hi> lately ſent over to plant; and <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merinds, Eldern, Goosberries, Curran Trees, Raſsberries, Pome-Citrons, Pome-Granats;</hi> and ſome ſay <hi>Plantins,</hi> and <hi>Bonano's.</hi> Certainly this Climate is deſtinated to ſolace the Native <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merican,</hi> and with the Bleſſings of Heaven to refreſh the ſolicitous <hi>European.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will expect a Collection or Breviary of thoſe <hi>Indian Kings</hi> on the Main of <hi>America;</hi> meaning ſuch Nations as are moſt Conſiderable (and border upon the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Settlements) which I ſhall readily impart unto them, as far as my Obſervation and Information directs to: but the Extent of the Province of <hi>Carolina,</hi> from <hi>Luck Iſland</hi> north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to <hi>St. Matheo</hi> ſouthward, is Seven or Eight Degrees:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52413:7"/>and in that ſpace there are many ſmall Nations remote from the Settlements, of which no account hitherto hath reached us. However, I'le firſt begin with <hi>Albemarle</hi> River, that lies in <hi>Roanoak,</hi> and is the extream Northern Settlement in <hi>Carolina;</hi> upon which head of the River the <hi>Tuſcarories</hi> dwell; and he's a <hi>Sagamore,</hi> or great Emperor of many Kings. But towards <hi>May</hi> River (and <hi>St Matheo</hi>) were the <hi>Weſtoe's,</hi> a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and war-like people, whoſe Kings are called <hi>Paracouſa's,</hi> and <hi>Warawanſes:</hi> but the Native <hi>Indians</hi> inhabiting in &amp; near to the preſent Settlements have only <hi>Cockawaſes,</hi> and are an effeminate people, and inconſiderable as to number. A Perſon of Honour that has travelled amongſt them, muſters them up but to ſeven, or eight Nations; and of ſeveral &amp; diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Languages; ſupine, and of a ſoft Nature; yet of good natural Parts, when to conſider their ſalvage Education, and the little advantages they have of Converſation: a broken uncultired, and unpoliſh't People in Government; and ſuch as formerly were chaſed from the Mountains, and compelled to ſeek ſanctuary in ſolitary Places; nor does any Nation amongſt them exceed Fifty Bowmen, as by the following Account.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Santeahs,</hi> which inhabit northward upon the rapid River <hi>Santee;</hi> they muſter but thirty Bowmen. And the <hi>Itawans</hi> upon <hi>Cooper</hi> River, formerly known by the Name of <hi>Wando;</hi> they conſiſt but of twenty Bowmen. Next to them are the <hi>Kiawahs,</hi> that dwell upon the skirts of <hi>Aſhley</hi> River; they reckon themſelves but forty Bowmen. More ſouthward to them are the <hi>Stonoes,</hi> upon the River <hi>Stonoh,</hi> adjoyning to <hi>Ediſto;</hi> which muſter but ſixteen Bowmen.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52413:8"/>And thoſe upon <hi>Ediſto</hi> to ſouthward, they ſeldom or never exceed ten Bowmen. But the <hi>Cuſſo's</hi> to the ſouthward of them, and planted upon <hi>Iſhepoo</hi> (now called <hi>Colleton</hi> River) are the greateſt Nation hereabout: yet they report of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be, but not to exceed fifty Bowmen. Then there's the <hi>Helena's,</hi> and they are a Nation yet more ſouther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that border upon the Banks of the Navigable River, <hi>St Helena;</hi> under conduct of a <hi>Warrawanſaw.</hi> And theſe War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers by computation are but thirty Bowmen, and no more. (In all) Two Hundred and Fourteen Bowmen; and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to live One Hundred Miles diſtant from North, to South; nor do they converſe, nor well underſtand the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of one another. Nor dwell they in Towns, but in ſtraggling Plantations; often removing for the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of Hunting, for that's their general Exerciſe, and a great part of their Maintenance; and which alſo ſo propagates their Health, that ſome of them live to ſee their Third, and Fourth; nay their Fifth Generation.</p>
            <p>Yet it's improbable they ſhould ever grow numerous, becauſe the Women deſtoy their Bellies with the decoction of a certain Bituminous Root, that naturally and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully grows every where amongſt them; which Root occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Stirility. And this ancient Cuſtom, becauſe practiſed from Generation to Generation, is ſo rivited into the faith of their Females; that neither Art, nor Argument can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon them to relinquiſh this Barbarity of deſtroying their Bellies, till arriving at the Age of twenty ſeven (or thereabouts) and then they fancy to themſelves that their Children (at ſuch years) will grow moſt active, vigorous,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52413:8"/>and valient; when their beſt Advance is but preferment to Bowmen. So that to me this ſeems an odd Practice; but who ſhall reclame it, except otherwiſe <hi>heaven</hi> it ſelf reduce them. Yet I'me convinc'd this Relation is true from the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of a worthy and honourable Perſon, that aſſured me ſuch are their Principles (and their Native Diſcipline) and becauſe conveighed from the Loins of Poſterity, its recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as an Oracle amongſt them; by which you may gueſs they are ſomewhat Superſtitious, without Idolatry: but that's remitted to the <hi>Reader</hi> to contemplate at leaſure.</p>
            <p>The Winter here in this ſouthern Latitude is moderate, and ſhort, and never exceeds one fifth of the year; and much of the temperature with our <hi>March</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> but never burdned with thoſe Diſtracting Bluſtring Eaſterly Winds, that beat back the Spring, and diſappoint the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Husbandman. For the Setlers in <hi>South Carolina,</hi> viz. upon <hi>Aſhley,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cooper</hi> Rivers. &amp;c they keep forth their Cattel all the year about, without occupying any hands to ſtore up Winter's Proviſion, as thoſe in <hi>New-England,</hi> and <hi>New-York</hi> do: but <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> and <hi>Pennſilvania</hi> muſt expoſe themſelves to Expence, Trouble, and Labour under a Chargeable Toil to get in their Winter's Fodder; which if to neglect by timely induſtry, their Stock, and Cattel muſt of neceſſity ſtarve. By which you may collect from the ſweet, and temperate Scituations of <hi>Carolina,</hi> that her Inhabitants (as its certainly true) uſually feed upon good and wholſom Fat Beef, in the months of <hi>November, December,</hi> and <hi>January. &amp;c</hi> Nor do they ſlaughter it from the Crib, or Stall; becauſe when only to drive it from the flouriſhing Savana's, where the Ox, and the Cow are all the year grazing.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52413:9"/>
            <p>This I ſhould think (with other Advantages) were enough to compenſate the modeſt Care, and Induſtry of the Setlers; beſides the natural propenſity of Love the Natives have, as if their Souls liv'd only in the boſom of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by natural inſtinct, becauſe when to proſtrate both themſelves and ſervices to fiſh, and hunt their Game for a Trifle; to fall Timber, to plant Corn, and to gather in their Crop: as alſo to pilot, and conveigh them from one Settlement to another. So that in many reſpects, the ſimple poverty of theſe indigent Natives ought by the Law of Kinde (and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity) to be ſweetned, and incouraged; if becauſe when to conſider their moral Civility, and innate Simplicity; which I hope the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Inhabitants in this fortunate ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Latitude will conſider, &amp; mingle with ſo much Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Moderation of Piety, as not to contrive them Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites; fatal to the Practice of <hi>New-England,</hi> becauſe when deſigning to convert them to <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here in theſe parts you may expect to meet with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Navigable Rivers; but of their Soundings I ſhall particularize more in my next: as alſo of their Rivulets, whoſe chriſtaline ſtreams are clear, and tranſparent. But their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhed Meadows, ſertil, and flouriſhing Savana's, are guarded with pleaſant and ſolitary Woods: beſides delicious Fields, and Paſtures that direct to Admiration. Which to numerate, as alſo to frame a Catalogue of the various Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of Fiſh, and their ſtore; whoſe prodigious increaſe here to inſert, I cannot. However, ſome of them are <hi>Shad, Sturgeon,</hi> and <hi>Salmon;</hi> omitting <hi>Whale,</hi> which are numerous in theſe Seas; ſo is the <hi>Seel</hi> or <hi>Selk,</hi> the <hi>Bottle-Noſe,</hi> and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52413:9"/>
               <hi>Porpus;</hi> beſides many other unctous Fiſh: but the <hi>Shark</hi> to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, wants Courage here, as indeed all other Ravenous Creatures do; for if they ſee but the Face of an Infant, they immediately fly. Another Claſſis are <hi>Drum, Porgee, Baſs, Boneto, Dolphin, Albechore, Sheepſheads, Oldwives, Catfiſh, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valle, Herin,</hi> and <hi>Mullets</hi> the largeſt in AMERICA. <hi>Trout</hi> alſo they have of two foot long, beſides the <hi>Pike,</hi> the <hi>Eel,</hi> and the <hi>Pearch;</hi> with ſeveral other freſh water Fiſh omitted (without conſent) in this Catalogue. And their Shell-fiſh are <hi>Crabs,</hi> better than thoſe in <hi>England;</hi> but <hi>Lobſters</hi> they have none that I hear of. However, <hi>Cokles,</hi> and <hi>Muſsles</hi> they have; and Banks, nay Mountains of <hi>Oyſters</hi> (and ſome with Pearl) that ſeem to barocade the Cricks. Beſides pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious <hi>Prawns,</hi> and <hi>Shrimps</hi> in the brackiſh, &amp; ſalt Waters, but <hi>Crawfiſh</hi> in the freſhes; which are various Entertainments, both to the Native, and fortunate Planter. But their Amphibions are <hi>Turtle, Bever, Otters, Manitee, Alegators, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And their Fleſhes are <hi>Beeves, Veals, Porks, Stagg,</hi> and <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Deer, Raccoons, Apoſſoms, Muttons, Lamb, Kid, Hare, Rabitt, &amp;c.</hi> But Ravenous Creatures are <hi>Wolves, Foxes, Bears, Panthers, Tygres:</hi> And their Venomous Creature is the <hi>Rattleſnake.</hi> Then there's Wild Fowl to Admiration; as <hi>Signets, Swants,</hi> &amp; <hi>Wild Turkies</hi> of incredible weight; beſides teems of <hi>Geeſe,</hi> and of ſeveral ſorts. There is <hi>Pheaſant</hi> alſo, <hi>Cranes,</hi> and <hi>Heronſhaws;</hi> the <hi>Woodcock,</hi> and <hi>Teal,</hi> with <hi>Snite, Jud, Poot, Morefowl, Curlue,</hi> and Covies of <hi>Partridges;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Plover</hi> great ſtore, green, and grey: There alſo are <hi>Turtle Doves, Feldivers, Sea Larks, Sande Levericks, Widgins,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52413:10"/>and <hi>Pidgeons</hi> numberleſs; beſides the <hi>Mockbird,</hi> with diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and variety of <hi>Singing Birds,</hi> and other feathered Fowl, that I cannot accompt for. Moreover, they have plenty of Dunghil Fowl, as the <hi>Cock,</hi> and <hi>Hen;</hi> the <hi>Gooſe,</hi> the <hi>Turkey,</hi> the <hi>Muſcovy</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Duck,</hi> &amp; <hi>Drake.</hi> Where alſo the Savana's are crowded with <hi>Deer,</hi> and large and ſtately Herds of Cattel patrole the Meadows, as Sheep the pleaſant Paſtures; and where every Field is repleniſh't with Corn, as are the <hi>Gardens</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi> enriched with choice Stone Fruits; but <hi>Almonds, Nectarines, Aprecot-Trees, Malagatoons,</hi> and the <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlin Plumb</hi> (the richeſt Stone Fruit in <hi>England</hi>) With divers other Trees, as the <hi>Bone Critton</hi> gon, and the <hi>Burgamy Pear;</hi> beſides <hi>Pippin Trees, Pearmains, Golden Ruſsitins, Harvey, Lady-finger,</hi> and <hi>Red-ſtreak,</hi> with various other Fruit Trees, now ſent over by the Honourable <hi>Sr Peter Colleton Bar.</hi> one of the <hi>Lords Proprietors.</hi> And ſeveral Fruit Trees, Flowers, and Roots, by divers other able <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and <hi>Merchants,</hi> that have already laid a Foundation in this ſouthern latitude of CAROLINA. Which I perſwade my ſelf will in a very few years, for Agriculture, and Tillidge, vye with the Glory of the whole World.</p>
            <p>Moreover, this beautiful <hi>Aurora,</hi> or the Riſing Sun of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica</hi> (known only by the Name of <hi>Carolina</hi>) is already courted by almoſt every Country: where note, it begins to depopulate ſome <hi>American Settlements,</hi> by reaſon of thoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couridgments propounded to all ſuch as ſtudiouſly ſolicit fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting her <hi>florid Fields.</hi> For in the firſt place, there's no Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of an <hi>Oath.</hi> Then in the next place, there's <hi>Toleration,</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> for people of Tender Conſcience; beſides Fifty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52413:10"/>Acres (but it formerly was One Hundred Acres) of Free Land, pointed at by the Conſtitutions; but that Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency is taken away, becauſe it hindred Community, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; and made the Setlers ſwell with great Plantations, when Unity and Popularity are the Nerve that combines preſervation. And Naturalization alſo is confirmed to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Individual and ſingle Perſon of any Kingdom, or Nation whatſoever (Male or Female) that tranſports him or her ſelf from any part of <hi>Europe;</hi> whereby they ſtand in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Capacity with the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Subjects, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priviledges in the aforeſaid Province of <hi>Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina;</hi> paying only the yearly acknowledgment of One Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an Acre, as a Quit-Rent to the Lords Proprietors; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencing in the year One Thouſand Six Hundred and Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and not before.</p>
            <p>Now to ſuch other <hi>neceſsitous perſons,</hi> as ſtand in no capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty capable to diſcharge their own Paſſage; yet is there Fifty Acres allotted unto them, notwithſtanding they come over as Servants; and their Proviſion and Accommodation the Diſpoſition and Charge of another: which proportion of Fifty Acres is ratified unto them after the expiration of the time contracted, and covenanted for by Indenture, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. But in caſe there be no Indenture, nor any viſible Contract; then in ſuch caſe that Servant uſually ſerves Four years, according to a Law of that Country, made practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all his Majeſties remote Governments, and Settlements in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Encouredgement enſues; that during the Service of ſuch Servant, be it Male, or Female; he or ſhe ſhall alſo be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52413:11"/>accommodated as the reſt of the free people are, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and convenient Clothing; and with all other things requiſit, and neceſſary. And further to ſtrengthen the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, when their Contract expires; the Maſter, or the Miſtriſs to whom ſuch Servant has ſerved his time honeſtly (and Conſcientiouſly) is by the Cuſtom of the Country to have Twelve Buſhels of <hi>Indian</hi> Corn, and a Firelock to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him whereby to live, and defend himſelf, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; as alſo to lay a Foundation for his future Maintenance: the like accommodation has every Woman-ſervant; ſave only the Fire Arms excepted.</p>
            <p>Moreover, in their time of ſervitude; here is no hard Impoſition put upon them, when <hi>Satturdy</hi> in the Afternoon is allowed them for Recreation (for Decency) and Repair of Apparel. And the <hi>Negro Slaves</hi> alſo have a ſhare of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to keep themſelves, their Houſes, and their Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſweet, and clean; becauſe the <hi>Lord's Day</hi> ought not to be prophaned, nor is any Perſon whatever privilidged to violate the <hi>Sabboth.</hi> Theſe are ſovereign Rules, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Preſidents, that direct towards a Religious Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and if I miſtake not, becomes the Duty of every <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;</hi> whoſe good Example of Piety and Virtue, will put a Spurr to others more remiſs; and encouridge all ſuch as ſeek their own future Welfare, in propagating the preſent Well-being of the Settlement and Setlers in <hi>Carolina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Europe</hi> nor the World has better Beeves, nor Sheep than what feed and graze in the Province of <hi>Carolina.</hi> Nor has any part on the Main of <hi>America</hi> greater variety of Fiſh, and Fowl (beſides Fruits, Plants, Roots, and Druggs) ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52413:11"/>that nothing is wanting to compleat it happy. But leſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure this Relation ſeem tedious to any, as its poſſible it may to ſome, more eſpecially to praevaricating Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (envious in Opinion) that would even ſubvert if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible the Fundamentals themſelves, and aſperſe the Country, by inſinuating their Malice into the Mouthes of Oppoſers; which would inevitably render the Colonies there but mean, and contemptible; and the truth of my Relation that alſo would they bring into ſuſpicion, whereby the <hi>Reader</hi> might ſuſpect the whole: for that end I thought requiſit to remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the particulars as above expreſt, to avoid all ſubtil Tricks, and Evaſions of ſuch as might otherwiſe inſence the plane; and ignorant Country-man, by telling him, <hi>That to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh his Native Climate, would expoſe him to more Miſery abroad, than Poverty and Penury would have made him Comfortleſs at home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I proceed to tell you, that the moſt uſeful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple adapted and fitted to carry on the Settlement, are Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks, and Artificers of all ſorts; as Gunſmiths, Lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths, Blackſmiths, Whiteſmiths, Farriers, Sadlers, Sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Tanners, Felmongers, Glovers, Shoemakers, Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Nailors, Joyners, Coopers, Carpenters, Sawyers <hi>(but no Lawyers)</hi> Brickmakers, Bricklayers, Potters, Hempdreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, Husbandmen; and all ſuch as are skilful in Cattel, and Agriculture: beſides Floreſts, Simplers, Druggiſts, Diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Bever, Caſtor, and Feltmakers. Of another rank are Vineroons; Gardners, Silkmakers, Throſters, Darymaids, Weavers, Spinſters, Knitters, Sempſters, good Houſwives, &amp;c. Theſe are the People that may enrich themſelves, and build up Eſtates in a ſhort time, whereby to make their Lives, and Poſterity happy; and by God's Permiſſion, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52413:12"/>ought I know; live long enough to enjoy them.</p>
            <p>For the Lords Proprietors (of whoſe Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I'le only touch upon) have thought it ſo much their own Intereſt, and Preſervation to make the people of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolina</hi> as eaſie as poſſible can be conſiſtant with any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and have parted with ſo much of their Rites, and Powers (which his <hi>Majeſty</hi> by his Patent Royal has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon them) that ſhould it ſo happen they could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their own Intereſt; yet is it out of their Power (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Proprietors) to do the meaneſt Setler any wrong. For the principal Power is lodged in an Aſſembly; and this Aſſembly is called the <hi>Grand Council,</hi> and <hi>Parliament;</hi> in which the Power of the Proprietor is ſo cautiouſly ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Nobility, and Commons elected into the ſame (by themſelves) that it would be more than difficult even in the executive part of the Government for the People thereby to receive any Detriment.</p>
            <p>Nor is there any <hi>Court of Juſtice</hi> in <hi>Carolina</hi> but what has its proper Judges by themſelves elected, and ſitting there to diſpence them Juſtice; in which every ſtate and condition of the people finds redreſs. So that other Nations may ſeem to envy ſuch Bleſſings, as not only to be tryed by their Peers, in point of Fact; but alſo in point of Law: though not intirely, yet in a ſufficient number to engage the Court to a Tendemeſs of the ſtate, and condition ſo tryed. And where as formerly by the <hi>Conceſsions,</hi> the major part of the Jury had the proper right of bringing in their Verdict; its now agreed upon, that all Juries choſen ſhall be grounded upon the ſame Baſis with our Engliſh Laws; and are the ſame vertually in point of Juſtice, ſave only the Juries in <hi>England</hi> are empan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell'd
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52413:12"/>by the <hi>County Sheriff,</hi> his Deputy, or the Clerk of the Court: but thoſe in <hi>Carolina</hi> are choſen by Lot out of the Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, which beyond diſpute is the moſt equal, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial way that wiſe men could have thought of.</p>
            <p>All theſe, and other Rites (which are many more) guarded by the primitive unalterable Conſtitutions of the Country, to which every new Setler ſubſcribes at his firſt arrival, if provided he approve thereof; and which by direction of one of the Fundamentals is publickly, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly to be read at the opening of every <hi>Parliament;</hi> to fix them ſteadfaſtly in the Hearts, and Minds of all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that they may do nothing in dimunition; nor contrive any Alteration of thoſe Fundamentals, which before they approved of: to which purpoſe they are alſo numbred, that at leaſt there may be none added, nor any embezled.</p>
            <p>So that the <hi>Parliament</hi> conſiſting of the Proprietors; &amp; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; who are either <hi>Landgraves,</hi> or <hi>Caſica's,</hi> made by colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a certain number of privilidg'd Lands under Grant from the Lords Proprietors; having an Heriditary Right of Ceſſion in <hi>Parliament,</hi> as alſo the Repreſentatives of the Commons elected have, that are ſent to ſit in Parliament. Theſe therefore have it fully and amply in their own Breſts (or any one ſtate thereof) to hinder and prevent any thing new, or unſafe, which ſhall be offered to be put upon them.</p>
            <p>And the Parliament thus qualified, and conſtituted out of the precedent Dignities, and Commons aforeſaid; have Power to enervate bad Practices, and encouridge good Laws; to ſtudy and contemplate the Promotion and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52413:13"/>growth of the Manufacture of the Country; to reform Ill manners, to ſtifle Vice, and ſuppreſs the Barbarity of ill Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms: to prohibit practice of Pleading for Reward; that neither directly, nor indirectly any Councel ſhall be retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Fee, nor flattered by the hope of a Gratuity; leſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure Law Suits be made chargeable, and vexatious; or a falſe Gloſs impoſed upon the Text, whereby to pervert a good Cauſe by privious and foreign Interpretation; or inſinuate a bad one, by prepoſtrous and delatory Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of the ſoveraign Privilidges of <hi>Carolina,</hi> whoſe Grandees to illuſtrate, I ſhall only ſuperſcribe the Lords Proprietors firſt; then the ſucceſſive Dignities, thoſe of the <hi>Land-Graves;</hi> after them the <hi>Caſica's,</hi> or <hi>Baronies;</hi> which with the praecedent Dignities are the Hereditary No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of <hi>Carolina,</hi> and are of the Council, and Parliaments; and are <hi>Delegates, Majeſtrates,</hi> and <hi>publick Miniſters of State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the peculiar Dignities that ſtand in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of CAROLINA, whoſe Eſtates are all intail'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Hiers Male; but for want of ſuch, upon Hiers Female; and when to conſider they are deſtitute of both; then in ſuch caſe its eſtabliſhed upon Heirs general. But preſuppoſing there be no general Hier, then ſuch Eſtate devolves to the <hi>Lords Proprietors;</hi> and the reaſon is, becauſe theſe Dignities from the greater to the leſſer are in a Capacity to be made Proprietors themſelves: for when a <hi>Lord Proprietor</hi> dyes without Iſſue, or as it may happen without a general Hier; then in ſuch caſe out of the inferiour Dignities, a <hi>Lord Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52413:13"/>(by the Fundamental Conſtitutions) is alwayes elected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Fortune</hi> (ſome will object) <hi>made not all men of one pitch' nor has ſhe rank't every man in one ſtation; nor preſcribes ſhe to every man a Co-equality in degree anſwerable to the praecedent Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications; what then, becauſe we are not all Lords, muſt we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be denyed the benefit of the Conceſsions.</hi> No ſurely, any man may better inform himſelf, if when to conſult the KINGS Royal Grant to the Lords Proprietors; which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains to every Subject an inherent Propriety, and Birth-right intail'd upon him; to which the Fundamental Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions agree: and where its well enough explain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fraud, and Ambiguity; that the Electors, and Setlers in <hi>Carolina,</hi> are by vertue of his Majeſty's Royal Grant made capable according to the Tenour, and Soccage of <hi>Eaſt-Greenwich</hi> in <hi>Kent;</hi> which enables them thereby to give, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath, alien, intitle, or diſpoſe of all, or any part of Lands, Goods, Chattels, and Heriditaments; when, and where, and to whom they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Another Branch of the Government is, that a general Liberty for people of tender Conſcience be alwayes tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without exception, or limitation. And the rather to ſtrengthen the nerve of this Toleration, the Lords Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors have confirm'd it in their Fundamentals: and where fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proviſion is alſo made, <hi>That no man Compel another to his Worſhip:</hi> nor gives it encouragement that any man double his own Faith whereby to digeſt the Formalities of a foreign Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Where note, all Civil and Religious Rites are granted without prohibition to all People, Nations, and Languages whatever profeſſing Piety, Vertue, and the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52413:14"/>to own One God (or Supream Being) the Maker of Heaven, and Earth; and that Jeſus Chriſt, the ever-living Son of God, is the divine Saviour of Mankind, and the World. So that as the Fundamentals have cautiouſly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for a Pious, &amp; Chriſtian Profeſſion; they have alſo made proviſion that no Profeſſor give another Interruption; ſo that they have ballanced their Clemency as equally as they could, whereby to diſpence to all alike.</p>
            <p>And where the Form (out of an implicit Faith) it zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly adorated, preſuppoſing it Life; whereby the Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor conſolates himſelf by the Contemplation of ſo dark a Viſion; yet ſo great is the Charity, and Law of the <hi>Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> in ſuch caſe, that the Peaceable Profeſſor of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Perſwaſion, may uſe it as an Argument to defend his Confeſſion; ſo that when to ſatisfie himſelf with his own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, it matters not though probably indiſpencible with another man's Opinion.</p>
            <p>And to theſe Privilidges of a pious Profeſſion, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions</hi> themſelves are Arguments, and Inducements ſtrong enough to encourage the modeſt, and ſober Profeſſor, whoſe Faith if it ſtand firm on the Baſis of Scripture; or if fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Principles of moral Precepts; the good preſidents of ſuch as practiſe Self-denyal; the Oracles and Inſpiration of the holy men of God; as the Apoſtles, the Patriarchs, and the Prophets, whoſe ſublime Speculation ſurmounted the glittering Orbs, to the beautiful ſeraphick ſociety of Angels, where the Divineſt dwells; who alſo dwells in the Hearts of Believers, to diſmember and break down the Monarchy of Sin: which glorious Victory gives us Triumph over Death, and leads Captivity captive. Theſe are ſacred Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilidges,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52413:14"/>and the Warfare of the Saints; and ought to be the Conteſt of every pious Profeſſor, who has freedom to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs as granted by the Conceſſions; but withal, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt not another at the time of Devotion, as he himſelf would not be interrupted; which if any does, he lies liable to Reproof, and the Penalties already laid down in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions.</p>
            <p>And this I admoniſh by way of Advice; that whoſoever premeditates tranſportation to <hi>Carolina:</hi> that he or ſhe if in the City (or the Suburbs) addreſs him or her ſelf to the <hi>Carolina Coffe-houſe,</hi> in <hi>Birchin-lane, London;</hi> there they may be entertained, or adviſed by ſome worthy and intelligeable Gentlemen, that will point out to them the illuſtrous Path to this ſalubrious Settlement: where the Rivers, and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulets, together with pleaſant Paſtures, and ſhady Savana's, moſt generouſly refreſh the Setlers. And beſides the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable iſſues of Health, they may alſo expect from thence Prolongation of Life (as by obſervation upon the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive) becauſe when to conſider the florid temperament of this ſouthern latitude, deſtinated to ſanity, by reaſon of an equality of Heart, and Cold ſo contempered together; that neither predominates.</p>
            <p>And what if it be objected <hi>I have publiſhed a Deſcription of a Country whereof hitherto I have only inſpected by Relation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out occular Proof.</hi> Yet ſo great is my Credit, and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thoſe worthy Gentlemen that uſhred it to me, as my faith confirms me that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s in <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> Where note, I recommend this Relation as the lively Emblem (and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter) as well as I can draw it of the now inhabited, and flouriſhing <hi>Carolina,</hi> the moſt hopeful Settlment the King of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52413:15"/>
               <hi>England</hi> has in <hi>America:</hi> which ſhort Proſpect may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſſen the Glory of ſo famous a Country, that may write it ſelf inferiour to none on the Continent; if when to conſider her minority, and the ſmall contingent Charge wherewith to lay a Foundation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Advice to Carolina.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE fundamental Being, and Well-being of all good and wholſom Government, depends meerly upon the Providence of God; to which when ſubjoyned the Piety of the Magiſtrate, it admits of a double Duty; to God firſt, then to the Magiſtrate, under whoſe Government we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, and expect peaceably to live, and enjoy the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Liberty; which Liberty conſiſts in the propriety of what God in his Wiſdom intails upon Poſterity, and intitles the inherent Birthright of every man born into the World; which hereafter I ſhall endeavour to explain, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe none amongſt you ſhall pretend to that impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Plea of Ignorance.</p>
            <p>Give me leave therefore to advice you to conſider the Footſteps of Age, that invades our preſtine flouriſhing Youth, whereby we cannot with vigour (and agillity of Body) perform that in act, and power; which in Youth we accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh't almoſt as ſoon as projected. But thoſe Defects are ſupplied by ſober, and moderate advice of Councel; and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52413:15"/>the Scriptures tell us, <hi>that in the multitude of Counſel there is ſafety;</hi> yet not that I think my ſelf worthy to advice you, though peradventure the Characters of Age have ſuperſcribed a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible date; and time if I miſtake not has ſuperanuated this mortal Fabrick, whereby what I intended to have told you by word of Mouth, conſtrains me now to commit that to paper; leſt retention of the one part, deprive you the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of the other.</p>
            <p>Inaſmuch therefore as every ſingle Subject is, or ought to be a Ruler, or Governour over his own Domeſticks; more properly ſuch is he that ſtands in a publick Capacity; and ſuch is the Majeſtrate, who by the Law of Religion, and Juſtice is bound in principles of Honour, and Conſcience to ſacrifice his Eſtate, and if need require his Life too, for the good of his Country: for that end, we ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thoſe proper and adequate mediums that intitle us to theſe ſupereminent Privilidges, which as <hi>Engliſh men</hi> we claim: and then to ruminate and contemplate ſuch pious Means, and Endeavours by the Law of Vertue, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, as are moſt requiſit, whereby to accompliſh them. On the other hand, omitting to challenge them, they by little and little will dwindle away, ſo in proceſs of time ſeem leſs; and at laſt become totally obliterated, that the future Generations will not know them to be.</p>
            <p>No man therefore in my Opinion is born only to gratifie himſelf, but is made in one capacity or other inſtrumental to ſerve the Country wherein he inhabits. The Piety whereof if ſeriouſly to conſider, as a <hi>gnomen</hi> directs the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to its proper Agent. And ſince Ends, and Beginnings have a like fate, and period. The appropriated ends there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52413:16"/>and the beginings of our Bleſſings ſpring properly and ſpontaneouſly from pious indications; which aſſigns it a Duty to our divine Creator. Then to expreſs our Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty without Hypocriſie to our Soveraign Lord the KING, as alſo our Fidelity to the <hi>Lords Proprietors;</hi> when becauſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail upon us (and Poſterity) the flouriſhing Fruits of an Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance in <hi>Carolina;</hi> which we may as naturally and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect, as the ends of the Creation predeſtinates Life the glorious Proſpect, and ſurveigh of the Creature.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> ſince ſo great and ſacred are the Ends of <hi>Government,</hi> &amp; the Priviledges of <hi>Parliaments</hi> as ſacred, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every Member, and Delegate thereof is permitted to ſpeak, and freely to ſpeak without heſitancy what he in himſelf ſhall hononrably think in reference to the good, and well fare of his Country whereof he himſelf is a Member. I exhort you therefore as <hi>Engliſh men</hi> to <hi>challenge</hi> to your ſelves this Native Privilidge, and the rather becauſe when to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your loyal Qualifications to ſuch inherent Rites, which all <hi>Engliſh men</hi> in <hi>Carolina</hi> naturally have, and are freely born there to; or if otherwiſe, they arive from foreign Ports, and not thoſe of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> yet they equally ſtand in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of this Bleſſing, though modeſtly to think themſelves in the remoteſt capacity.</p>
            <p>And this royal Privilidge naturally ſprings from a Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Grant of our gracious Prince, as in the <hi>Patent;</hi> and not only to the <hi>Engliſh</hi>-born in <hi>England,</hi> but ſuch others alſo as fall in with the <hi>Conceſsions</hi> of <hi>Carolina.</hi> For you are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that in his Majeſty's Charter or Royal Grant to the <hi>Lords Proprietors,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> there makes no diſtinction betwixt thoſe his native Subjects born in <hi>England;</hi> and thoſe others implanted and born in <hi>America.</hi> And as there can be no <hi>inter
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52413:16"/>Regnum</hi> in Kingſhip, ſo the <hi>Lords Proprietors</hi> have provided in the <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> and upon ſerious conſideration the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> have reſolved, <hi>That no man be diſinherited his Birthright, except his Offence exceed the limit of a Pardon.</hi> And becauſe this Privilidge ſhines from the Prince himſelf, the more it confirms and <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rengthens the Obligation; except to diſloyal, and ſuperlative ingrates and others, whoſe perfidy detects their fidelity, and would nouriſh themſelves with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy; were not ſuch deprived the natural encouridgment of the Country.</p>
            <p>Now peradventure ſome ſuch Antichriſtian Runagado's of Religion and Loyalty, tacitly recide conceal'd amongſt you; meaning Pretenders to Sanctity who ſhelter, and hide themſelves under the Government, till opportunity preſents to diſplay their more infamous Lives. Such Loyalty hangs meerly on the Slit of a Pen, and the beſt of their Religion ſtands on the Tip of their Tongues. Theſe men therefore when diſcovered, its not amiſs I think that all ſuch Hereticks of the Weal Publick be expun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all vertuous Society. So that if when diſcountenanced by the Majeſtrate, and the well-meaning Planter; their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie will make but a ſlender progreſs, and get as ſmall growth in the Colonys of <hi>Carolina,</hi> as the boaſting <hi>Roman</hi> thought to gain Honour from the <hi>Senators</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> when to magnifie his own illuſtrous Extraction; and decry <hi>Cicero</hi>'s, becauſe to ſpring from the ſhrubs of a Cottage. Now its true, every thing muſt have a begining; and <hi>Carolina</hi> though but now in the bloſſom, yet ſhe may live to bring forth more <hi>Cicero's,</hi> than boaſting <hi>Thraſo's;</hi> and in time grow up to ſuch compleat maturity, that her Proſperity will be emulated by thoſe on the Continent.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52413:17"/>
            <p>Where note <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you are to conſider, that as the King's Royal Grant gave Birth to <hi>Carolina;</hi> ſo it gives Power to the <hi>Lords Proprietors</hi> to make what ſutable proviſion they themſelves think fit whereby to conduct, &amp; improve the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. Which rightly to interpret; the <hi>Lords Proprietors</hi> have already given demonſtration of the<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> good endeavours in ſetling the Colonys there; which appropriates a double obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, if the people wiſe enough to improve it; and I hope they will, otherwiſe they forfeit their Gratitude to their Prince; and their Reputation if any to the generous intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Lords Proprietors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> as the <hi>Lords Proprietors</hi> have unanimouſly correſponded to ſettle this Province of <hi>Carolina;</hi> ſo by the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> they do promiſe the Planters to eſtabliſh ſuch good, and wholſom Laws amongſt them; whereby the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> as the People, may be bleſt. Which if anſwered by the Careful Induſtry of the Planter; the iſſue may alike prove profitable: and the rather if they propoſe to proceed upon <hi>Wines, Oyles, Smyrna Cotten, Rice,</hi> and <hi>Indego;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun upon. And as <hi>Silk, Almonds, Dates, Currans, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, Sena, Jeſſemy,</hi> and <hi>Rubarb</hi> are intended. But the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince naturally produces the <hi>China Root, Saſſafras, Saſſape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilla, Snakeweed,</hi> and that famous Vegetable called <hi>Calubria</hi> (in whoſe ſeedy Pod the <hi>Coochenial Fly</hi> germinates) is already tranſported, and thrives beyond Report. Beſides which, there are many and various other profitable <hi>Plants, Druggs,</hi> and <hi>Roots</hi> deſigned the enſuing progreſs of ſome of the principal <hi>Projectors;</hi> which in due time may fall in with the reaſon of the people in general, to make them more Rich, and Happy; than otherwiſe their preſent Proſpect directs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52413:17"/>to: which to inſpect, its neceſſary they conſult the natural propenſity of the Soil, whereby to enable the <hi>Planter,</hi> if ſolicitous after the Profits.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> whereas one material circumſtance was omitted in the <hi>Preſent State of Carolina;</hi> I thought requiſit and neceſſary to inſert it in the <hi>Advice;</hi> and that is, <hi>whereas the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Lords Proprietors of</hi> Corolina <hi>out of a ſingular tenderneſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the people coming on, as alſo the Planter already ſetled there, have ratified, and confirmed fifty Acres of Land to be eſtated for ever upon every individual Setler, or Setlers; he or they paying only one penny an Acre as a Quit Rent to the Lords Proprietors after two years time, So out of a ſerious and judicial conſideration, and reſpect to the Setler, and others intending to ſettle there; the ſaid Lords Proprietors have agreed among themſelves, that whoſoever ſets dowm as a ſetler in</hi> Carolina <hi>may contract with them here to become purchaſers, at the rate of five Pounds Sterling for one hundred Acres; and ſo to take up as much as they pleaſe, and ſtand acquitted forever of any Quit Rent, by the bare acknowledgment only of a</hi> Pepper Corn (<hi>or</hi> one Grane of Indian Corn) <hi>once a year, if when thereto required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> if you ſtand obleiged in more than a ſingle capacity, in a double acknowledgement you ought to anſwer it; and the Expedient will hardly prove grevious; for if when to conſider that the <hi>Lords Proprietors</hi> acquire on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reading the <hi>Fundamental Conſtitutions</hi> at the <hi>general Ceſsion,</hi> or opening of every <hi>Parliament;</hi> the reaſon you are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is, <hi>That the Laws being read, and made publick; the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof will appear the more eaſie.</hi> And often to imprint them in the minds of the people, their frequent and conſtant uſe will inſinuate into the Ignorant. Otherwiſe, how can he be ſaid to ſin, that never tranſgreſt: nor can that People
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52413:18"/>be manifeſt Tranſgreſſors, where there's no known Law to offend.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fundamental Conſtitutions</hi> therefore being to be read at the opening of every <hi>Parliament,</hi> its my Advice <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that you obſerve this Decorum, <hi>That his Majeſty's Royal Grant be alſo praecedently read before the Conſtitutions;</hi> and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to furniſh every Majeſtrate, and other inferiour Officer with Arguments to enervate the Prejudicate (if any) and ſuch Emulators of Ve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue as ſtudy to arreſt, and would if poſſible ſubvert the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> themſelves. Moreover, it will ſtrengthen the Nerve of Unity, and Friendſhip of ſuch as labour to promote the Proſperity of <hi>Carolina;</hi> and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Endeavours of malicious Agents, that would ſtifle if poſſible the Welfair of the Settlement. So that as the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Formality nothing in it ſelf degenerates from Loyalty; the Clemency, and Benignity of your Prince were a Sin to ſuſpect: conſequently an Evil unpardonable to dought the Honourable Intention of the <hi>Lords Proprietors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſidue <hi>Gentlemen</hi> are only ſome indigeſted Particulars that point to the Growth, Conveniency, and Manufacture of the Country; the Regularity of Living, and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Life: the Medium for Manners, and the good and happy iſſues of Proſperity to the Settlement, and its long Duration. The Incorporating of Towns, and enabling them with ſuch ſoveraign and whoſome Laws, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidges as may neither hurt the Planter, nor terrifie the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try man; nor raiſe ambitious hopes in Artizan or Cirizen to ſwell Corporations with unbounded Charters, that may bring an inconeniency upon the bordering Colonies.</p>
            <p>The introducing of Studds (from a good ſtrain of Horſes)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52413:18"/>are of abſolute Neceſſity; where note, every man of Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility ought to endeavour it. And ſuch alſo as cultivate, and labour the Ground for encreaſe of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Grain, deſerve a ſignal Encouragment. The building of Ships, and other Veſſels for Tranſportation: and erecting Bridges for Horſes, Carts, and Carridges; are alſo worthy your ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. So to lay out large, and regular High Wayes, and to raiſe formidable, and durable Fortifications; with many other requiſit Circumſtances, and Conveniences me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit a reſpect. But theſe will fall in courſe; and are more properly tranſmitted to the mature Gravity, and deliberate Conſideration both of <hi>Council,</hi> and <hi>Parliament;</hi> ſo draw on to a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>But I hope <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you'l excuſe my Brevity (and my Errors too, when you meet them) its true, I preſent you but with a ſhort proſpect of ſo glorious a Country, that beyond diſpute is inferiour to none on the Continent. And truly ſuch were my Cautions, as cautiouſly kept me cloſe to the truth of diſcovery; which has been handed to me by ſeveral good, and worthy <hi>Gentlemen;</hi> but principally from a Perſon of Honour, and Quality (a Setler amongſt them) whoſe generous nature, and freedom to diſcourſe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (and furniſh me with all or moſt of his Diſcoveries) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a Recompence beyond my Acknowledgements: which with Gratitude I would readily publiſh to the World, but his Commands obleidge me tacitly to conceal him.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I ſhall leave you but one Caution more, (the reſt I'le huddle in ſilence) and that is, to be cautious of your ſelves, whereby to think no diſhonourable Thought; for I reckon it a Maxim in Philoſophy, and I'me ſure its
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52413:19"/>within the Rules of <hi>Chriſtianity: That every man ſtudy the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Honeſty.</hi> For to be diſhoneſt within our ſelves, is to doubt the Faith of others; ſo at laſt our Scruples redounding too oft upon us, honeſty it ſelf will be brought into ſuſpicion; and the Prudence and Juſtice of men in Government, but Toys, and Trifles of the times to play with. This contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on let every man labour to ſuppreſs, becauſe its a Child of Ingratitude; and Ingratitude's a Sin of that nature, that Heaven can hardly pardon. Wherefore <hi>Carolina</hi> beware of Ingratitude, and think no thought diſhonourable; nor doubt the Faith of thoſe that ſtreneouſly labour to do you good. Reverence your Creator with a holy Fear; and with a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Love be charitable to your Country: with an awful reſpect give your Services to the <hi>Proprietors;</hi> and with a Loyal Duty your Obedience to your <hi>Soveraign,</hi> whom <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> preſerve to enlarge his Empire, and ſtrengthen the hands of the preſent Undertakers.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THere is one Mr. <hi>Nathan Sumers</hi> Engineer for <hi>Carolina,</hi> that hath undertaken [by a new Engin of his own] with the <hi>Lords Proprietors,</hi> and others, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden, and clear the Ground to fit it for Cultivation at 12 d. a Tree, if not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 6. foot diameter; and for 6 d. a Tree from one foot to more than 5 inches dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter. And that the ſaid <hi>Proprieters</hi> have contracted with the ſaid <hi>Sumers,</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to him and his Hiers the ſole uſe, and benefit of the ſaid Invention for 14 years, as certify'd.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Omiſſions and Errata's.</head>
            <p>Pag. 7 line 3 for ſalubrous read ſalubrious. p 13 l 10 f Cockawaſes r Cockarouſes. l. 17 f un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultired r uncultivated. p 22 l 7 r Powers as to decline their Negative Voice. l 26. Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiors, but thoſe Conceſsions were falſly printed.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
